Sinclair mss. IV, 1900-1963 LMC 1967
Lilly Library
Sinclair mss. IV
1900-1963
Lilly Library
Sinclair, Mary Craig (Kimbrough), 1883-1961
LMC 1967
11 Boxes 11 standard
The Sinclair mss. IV, 1900-1963, consists of correspondence, writings, and monetary statements of author Upton Beall Sinclair, 1878-1968, and of his wife, Mary Craig (Kimbrough) Sinclair, 1883-1961.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchase: 1973
Biographical Note
Upton Beall Sinclair, 1878-1968, author; and Mary Craig (Kimbrough Sinclair), 1883-1961, author.
Scope and Contents
The Sinclair mss. IV, 1900-1963, consists of correspondence and writings of author Upton Beall Sinclair, 1878-1968, and of his wife, Mary Craig (Kimbrough) Sinclair, 1883-1961. Writings include American Nights Entertainment, Love's Progress, and The Story of Craig by Upton Sinclair; The Gold Spangled Banner by Edgar Selwyn and Upton Sinclair, and My Husband, Upton Sinclair by Mary Craig (Kimbrough) Sinclair. Agreements & Copyrights include royalty reports and statements from Albert and Charles Bonu, Boni and Liveright, Farrar and Rinehart, and T. Wener Laurie, and Viking Press. Miscellaneous includes various items related to The Cup of Fury, King Coal, Southern Belle, telepathy & hypnotism, and miscellaneous writing fragments. Personal includes bank statements and cancelled checks.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series: I. Correspondence, II. Writings, III. Agreements and Copyrights, IV Royalties, V. Miscellaneous, and VI. Personal Papers, VII. The Brass Check By Upton Sinclair and Notes
Related Materials
See Sinclair mss., Sinclair mss. II, Sinclair mss. III, Sinclair mss. V, Sinclair mss. VI, Sinclair mss. VII, Sinclair mss. VIII, Sinclair, D. mss., and Sinclair, M.C.K. mss., also located at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana.
Journalism; Labor unions and socialism; Sinclair, Mary Craig; Sinclair, Upton, 1878-1968
- Correspondence (Box 1, Box 2)
  - Biographic Materials (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1900-1914 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1915-1917 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1919-1924 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1927-1934 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1935 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1936-1939 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1940-1944 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1945 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1948 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1949 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1950 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1951 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Jan. 1952 - June 1952 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - July 1952 - Dec. 1952 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Jan. 1953 - July 1953 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Aug. 1953 - Dec. 1953 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Jan. 1954 - Aug. 1954 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Sept. 1954 - Dec. 1954 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Jan. 1955 - June 1955 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - July 1955 - Dec. 1955 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Jan. 1956 - June 1956 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - July 1956 - Dec. 1956 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Jan. 1957 - Sept. 1957 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Oct. 1957 - Nov. 1957 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Dec. 1957 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Jan. 1958 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Feb. 1958 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Mar. 1958 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Apr. 1958 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - May 1958 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - June 1958 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - July 1958 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Aug. 1958 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - September 1, 1958 - September 14, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Sept. 15, 1958 - Sept. 19, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Sept. 20, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Sept. 21, 1958 - Sept. 30, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Oct. 1, 1958 - Oct. 9, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Oct. 10, 1958 - Oct. 31 - 1958 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Nov. 1, 1958 - Nov. 15, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Nov. 16, 1958 - Nov. 30, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Dec. 12, 1958 - Dec. 9, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Dec. 10, 1958 - Dec. 19, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Dec. 20, 1958 - Dec. 31, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - 1958 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Jan. 1959 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Feb. 1959 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Mar. 1959 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Apr. 1959 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - May 1959 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - June 1959 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - July 1959 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Aug. 1959 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Sept. 1959 - Dec. 1959 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Jan. 1960 - Apr. 1960 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - May 1960 - Dec. 1960 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - 1961-1963 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Letters to Sinclair, Upton Beall (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - A-Z (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Letters from Sinclair, Upton Beall (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Letters From Sinclair, Mrs. M.C.K. A-G (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Letters From Sinclair, Mrs. M.C.K. (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Letters From Sinclair, Mrs. M.C.K. H-K (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Letters From Sinclair, Mrs. M.C.K. L (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Letters From Sinclair, Mrs. M.C.K. M-Z (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Letters From Sinclair, Mrs. M.C.K. Misc., etc. (Box 2, Folder 69)
- Writings (Box 2, Box 3, Box 4, Box 5)
  - American Nights Entertainment (1) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - American Nights Entertainment (2) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - American Nights Entertainment (3) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Gold-Spangled Banner (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Selwyn & Sinclair (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Love's Progress (Box 3)
    - Books I-IV, Early Draft (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Books, V-VIII, Early Draft (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Books, IX-XI, Early Draft (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Books, XII-XIV, Early Draft (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Misc. Papers (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Books, I-IV, Later Draft. Carbon (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Books, I-IV, Later Draft (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Books, V-IX, Later Draft (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Books, V-IX, Later Draft. Carbon (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Books, X-XIV, Later Draft. Carbon (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Books, X-XIV, Later Draft (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - My Husband, Upton Sinclair (Box 3)
    - 1.0 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - 2.0 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - 3.0 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - 4.0 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - 5.0 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - 6.0 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - 7.0 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - 8.0 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - 9.0 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - 10.0 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - 11.0 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - 12.0 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - 13.0 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - 14.0 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - 15.0 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - The Story of Craig (Box 4)
    - Early Draft 1 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Early Draft 2 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Early Draft 3 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Early Draft 4 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Later Draft 1 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Later Draft 2 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Later Draft 3 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Later Draft 4 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Later Draft 5 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Theirs be the Guilt (Box 4)
    - 1.0 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - 2.0 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Revisions of Manassass (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Re: Theirs be the Guilt (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Young Lanny Buddy (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Short Articles A-Z (Box 4)
    - American Dancers (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Artificial Selection (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - A Boy And The Law: A Boy Who Might Have Been You (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Columbia Square Hollywood Speech (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Concerning Lanny Budd (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - The Death of Franklin D. Roosevelt, The Double Standard (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - George Sterling: God as a Suggestion (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - I Saw Red for a Nickel (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - The Indignant Subscriber (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - Introducing a University President (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Little Halls for Radicals (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - Living in the Single Tax Colony at Arden, Delaware (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - The Magic Hunters (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - Mr. And Mrs. Franklin Smith (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - Orangevale (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - Restore and Keep Your Health (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - The Sacred Sword (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - This is how it Is (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - Utopia Americana (Box 4, Folder 64)
    - A Visit to Boston (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - Voice of America (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - A War of Words over Words (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - The Way Out: What Lies Ahead of America (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - Why we can Win (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - Worlds Apart (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Worlds End Impending (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - Writings by Other Authors A-Z (Box 4)
    - Writings by Other Authors (Box 4, Folder 72)
    - Birnbaum, Martin. Adventures in the World of Art. Early Draft (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - Birnbaum, Martin. Adventures in the World of Art. Later Draft (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - "Dear Janey," Part I (Box 4, Folder 75)
    - "Dear Janey," Part II (Box 4, Folder 76)
    - Kelly, Mrs. Edith (Summers). Helicon Hall: An Experiment in Living (Box 4, Folder 77)
    - Lewis, Sinclair. Introduction to Edith Summers Kelley's Weeds (Box 4, Folder 78)
    - Packers Peter. Appointment with a Nobody (Box 4, Folder 79)
    - Sinclair, Bettina and Trilling, Diana Snitkinz (Box 4, Folder 80)
- Agreements and Copyrights (Box 5)
  - General, 1927-1946 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Another Pamela, 1949-1954 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Appeal to Reason. 1, 1920 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Between Two Worlds. 4, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Book of Life. 1, 1923 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Cicero. 1, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Coop. 1, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Doctor First. 1, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Dragon Harvest. 5, 1944-1951 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Dragon's Teeth. 1, 1941-1942 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - "The Enemy Had it Too." 1, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Expect no Peace (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Front Page Challenge. 1, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - A Giant's Strength. 1, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - The Jungle. 4, 1906-1958 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Lanny Budd Series. 6, 1943-1954 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Index to the Lanny Budd Story. 1, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Love's Pilgrimage. 1, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Mammonart. 2, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - "Mission from Marrekech." 1, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - "Most Haunted House." 3, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Mountain City. 1, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - My First Eighty Years. 4, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Oil. 1, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - One Clear Call. 6, 1948-1952 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Our Lady. 1, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - A Personal Jesus. 7, 1952-1954 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Presidential Agent. 4, 1943-1949 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Presidential Mission. 6, 1947-1949 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - The Return to Lanny Rudd. 7, 1952-1953 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Upton Sinclair Presents W. Fox (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Wayland, J.A., Biography. 1, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - The Wet Parad. 1, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - What Didymus Did. 3, 1954-1955 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Wide is the Gate. 6, 1942-1944 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - A World to Win. 3, 1945-1949 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - World's End. 3, 1940-1942 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - A.D. Peters, 1929-1941 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Agencia Literaria Dona Carlota, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Albert & Charles Boni., 1927-1933 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Alfred Scherz Verlag., 1945 - June 30, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Alfred Scherz Verlag, July 1, 1955 - 1963 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Andrew H. Dakers., 1924-1928 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Allan Wingate, 1954-1956 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Arnoldo Mondadori, 1951-1963 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Bernhard Tauchnity, 1932-1937 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Bob-Merril Co., Inc., 1962-1963 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Boni & Liverright Publishers, 1923 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Cal Ann-Levy, Editeurs, 1955-1957 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Channel Press, 1956-1963 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Crown Publishers, 1957-1959 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Czechoslovakian, 1951-1962 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - De Arbeiderspers, 1955-1960 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Dial Press, Inc., 1943-1951 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Diana Verlag Zürich, 1952-1960 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Doubleday, Doran & Co, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Editions Bourrelier, 1959-1962 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Editions Mondiales, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Editorial Claridad, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Editorial Palesttra, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Farrar & Rinehart, Inc., 1932-1936 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Farrar &U Rinehart, Inc., 1937-1940 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - George Allen & Unwin, Ltd., 1954-1960 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - H. Aschehoug & Co., Oslo., 1950-1962 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Harcourt, Brace & World, Inc., 1962 (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Humata Verlag, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Hungarian, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Hutchinson, 1919-1935 (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - Jacob Muchnik, Ed., 1956 (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - John. C. WInston, Co., 1921-1924 (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Jugoslovenska Autorska Agencija, 1956-1957 (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Kojitsu Shokan, 1953-1955 (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Little Blue Books., 1956 (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Malik-Verlag, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Mayfair Booths, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Murray & Gee, Inc., 1943-1945 (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - N.V. Servire, 1953-1960 (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - Pocketbooks, Inc., 1962-1963 (Box 5, Folder 78)
  - Rand McNally & Co. N.D. (Box 5, Folder 79)
  - Rodale Press., 1939 (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - Societe des Auteurs & Compositeurs dramatiques, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 81)
  - Sagamore Press, Inc., 1958-1960 (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - Sol Lesser Productions, Inc., 1954-1955 (Box 5, Folder 83)
  - Sudamericana, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 84)
  - Steinberg Verlag, 1960-1962 (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - T. Werner Laurie, Ltd., 1918-1932 (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - T. Werner Laurie, Ltd., 1933-1935 (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - T. Werner Laurie, Ltd., 1936-1937 (Box 5, Folder 88)
  - T. Werner Laurie, Ltd., 1938 (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - T. Werner Laurie, Ltd., 1939-1940 (Box 5, Folder 90)
  - T. Werner Laurie, Ltd., 1941 (Box 5, Folder 91)
  - T. Werner Laurie, Ltd., 1942-1944 (Box 5, Folder 92)
  - T. Werner Laurie, Ltd., 1945-1950 (Box 5, Folder 93)
  - T. Werner Laurie, Ltd., 1953-1954 (Box 5, Folder 94)
  - T. Werner Laurie, Ltd., 1955-1958 (Box 5, Folder 95)
  - Tami Publishing Co., 1951-1953 (Box 5, Folder 96)
  - Thomas Books, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 97)
  - Twayne Publishers, Inc., 1960-1962 (Box 5, Folder 98)
  - Univ. of Missouri Press., 1961-1963 (Box 5, Folder 99)
  - Vanguard Press, Inc., 1938-1942 (Box 5, Folder 100)
  - Verlag für Literature und Zeitgeschehen, 1961-1963 (Box 5, Folder 101)
  - Western Printing & Lithographing Co., 1923 (Box 5, Folder 102)
  - Wilco Publishing House, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 103)
- Royalties (Box 6)
  - Viking Press (Box 6)
    - General Statements, 1948-1962 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Another Pamela, 1950-1957 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Between Two Worlds, 1942-1958 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Dragon Harvest, 1945-1958 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Dragon's Teeth, 1942-1958 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - The Enemy Had It Too, 1950-1957 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - The Jungle, 1946-1962 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - O Shepherd Speak!, 1949-1958 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - One Clear Call, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Presidential Agent (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Presidential Mission (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - The Return of Lanny Budd (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Wide Is The Gate (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - A World to Win (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - World's End (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Miscellaneous (Box 7)
  - Lists (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Re: Cup of Fury (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Re: King Coal (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Re: Southern Belle (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Southern Bell Fragment (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Re: Telepathy/Hypnotism (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - A Sensory Theory of Hypnotism (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - 1 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - 2 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - 3 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - 4 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - 5 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - 6 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - 7 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - 8 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - 9 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - 10 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - 11 (Box 7, Folder 18)
- Personal Papers (Box 8, Box 9, Box 10)
  - Bank Statements and Canceled Checks (Box 8)
    - 1924-1927 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - 1934-1938 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - 1942-1947 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - 1948 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - 1.0, 1954 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - 2.0, 1954 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - 3.0, 1954 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - 4.0, 1954 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - 1.0, March - Oct. 1955 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - 2.0, Oct. - Dec. 1955 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - 1.0, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - 2.0, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - 1.0, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - 2.0, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - 1958 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Checks, Deeds, Insurance Papers, Mortgages, Tax Receipts (Box 9)
    - 1907-1920 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - 1921-1923 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - 1924-1925 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - 1926-1930 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - 1931-1947 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - 1948-1950 (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - 1951-1954 (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - 1955-1959 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Income Tax Reports (Box 10)
    - 1927-1942 (Box 10, Folder 24)
    - 1943-1946 (Box 10, Folder 25)
    - 1947-1949 (Box 10, Folder 26)
    - 1950-1954 (Box 10, Folder 27)
    - 1955-1959 (Box 10, Folder 28)
- The Brass Check by Upton Sinclair and Notes (Box 11)